<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Minimind - Artificial Intelligence</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/artificial-intelligence.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2014-04-02T10:06:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>A robot with evolved morphology and controller</title><link href="/a-robot-with-evolved-morphology-and-controller.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-04-02T10:06:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-04-02T10:06:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Ian Macinnes</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-04-02:/a-robot-with-evolved-morphology-and-controller.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My doctorate back in 2006 was partly research on evolving the morphologies of
robots and controllers in simulation and then constructing them. Most of the robots
are now lost but today I discovered these movies of a single example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fitness function of the population of robots was simply to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My doctorate back in 2006 was partly research on evolving the morphologies of
robots and controllers in simulation and then constructing them. Most of the robots
are now lost but today I discovered these movies of a single example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fitness function of the population of robots was simply to move.
The population size was 30. The robot uses a continuous time recurrent neural network as a controller, co-evolved
with the morphology over 1000 generations. This was the fittest agent from the final generation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/ZTLnDFlsDiw?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the agent after it was physically constructed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/ztQFTryLq5A?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting aspect is the curved arms that were evolved to allow the robot to
roll over, then roll back.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Artificial Intelligence"></category></entry><entry><title>Acroban the Humanoid</title><link href="/acroban-the-humanoid.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-08-13T18:34:00+01:00</published><updated>2010-08-13T18:34:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Ian Macinnes</name></author><id>tag:None,2010-08-13:/acroban-the-humanoid.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting robot from &lt;a title="Inria Flowers home page" href="http://flowers.inria.fr/index.php" target="_blank"&gt;Inria Flowers&lt;/a&gt;
that was showcased at the ACM SIGGRAPH Conference that's just finished. The robot has a fixed rather than random morphology but it is a
very nice example of a real physical robot with two legs and a torso being able to balance …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting robot from &lt;a title="Inria Flowers home page" href="http://flowers.inria.fr/index.php" target="_blank"&gt;Inria Flowers&lt;/a&gt;
that was showcased at the ACM SIGGRAPH Conference that's just finished. The robot has a fixed rather than random morphology but it is a
very nice example of a real physical robot with two legs and a torso being able to balance in the face of perturbations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/zHbl-ozA_h0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it can balance itself in the face of minor knocks and shakes, it doesn't walk like a human. A walking human
keeps moving their centre of gravity forward so one foot has to be placed ahead to stop the body falling. In fact, human walking
has been described as controlled falling. Acroban appears to be careful to keep its centre of gravity above support points (i.e. its feet)
so it won't tip over. This is why is moves so slowly. Still a very nice robot though! Anything that tall that's constantly
moving that can balance itself is a tremendous achievement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Artificial Intelligence"></category></entry><entry><title>Virtual creatures gallery 3 of 10</title><link href="/virtual-creatures-gallery-3-of-10.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-08-12T16:34:00+01:00</published><updated>2010-08-12T16:34:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Ian Macinnes</name></author><id>tag:None,2010-08-12:/virtual-creatures-gallery-3-of-10.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is another post in an occasional series of other peoples'
videos of evolved virtual creatures.
&lt;a title="Stellar Alchemy home page" href="http://www.stellaralchemy.com/lee/index.php" target="_blank"&gt;Lee Graham of Stellar Alchemy&lt;/a&gt; has
produced great &lt;a title="Virtual creature video at YouTube" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GqHybJaBXYI" target="_self"&gt;virtual&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a title="Virtual creature video at YouTube" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QPEjzxjxXoM" target="_self"&gt;creatures&lt;/a&gt;, some of which
move beautifully. He keeps a &lt;a title="Zoo of virtual creatures at Stella Alchemy" href="http://www.stellaralchemy.com/lee/vce3d_favorites.php"
target="_self"&gt;zoo of the best&lt;/a&gt; that people have sent in using his software. I especially like the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is another post in an occasional series of other peoples'
videos of evolved virtual creatures.
&lt;a title="Stellar Alchemy home page" href="http://www.stellaralchemy.com/lee/index.php" target="_blank"&gt;Lee Graham of Stellar Alchemy&lt;/a&gt; has
produced great &lt;a title="Virtual creature video at YouTube" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GqHybJaBXYI" target="_self"&gt;virtual&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a title="Virtual creature video at YouTube" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QPEjzxjxXoM" target="_self"&gt;creatures&lt;/a&gt;, some of which
move beautifully. He keeps a &lt;a title="Zoo of virtual creatures at Stella Alchemy" href="http://www.stellaralchemy.com/lee/vce3d_favorites.php"
target="_self"&gt;zoo of the best&lt;/a&gt; that people have sent in using his software. I especially like the movement of some of these and also the
music playing, since normally virtual creature videos are deathly silent. This is my favourite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/lhZthzFLams" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Artificial Intelligence"></category></entry><entry><title>The behaviour-based robotics revolution</title><link href="/the-behaviour-based-robotics-revolution.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-08-11T10:24:00+01:00</published><updated>2010-08-11T10:24:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Ian Macinnes</name></author><id>tag:None,2010-08-11:/the-behaviour-based-robotics-revolution.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I mentioned Rodney Brooks in an earlier post so I though I'd briefly write a profile of Brooks and the behaviour-based robotics revolution he
helped start at the beginning of the 1990's. Rodney Brooks is an Austrialian who, after a series of insightful and highly influential
papers, eventually ascended to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I mentioned Rodney Brooks in an earlier post so I though I'd briefly write a profile of Brooks and the behaviour-based robotics revolution he
helped start at the beginning of the 1990's. Rodney Brooks is an Austrialian who, after a series of insightful and highly influential
papers, eventually ascended to head the &lt;a title="Artificial Intelligence Laboratory at MIT home page" href="http://www.csail.mit.edu" target="_blank"&gt;Artificial Intelligence Laboratory at MIT&lt;/a&gt; from 2003 to 2007. He brought various issues into the mainstream of the field, but I&amp;#8217;ll discuss functional and behavioural decomposition here, rather than his fascinating arguments for &lt;a title="The distinction between being situated and being embodied" href="http://www.evolvingmorphologies.com/?p=11" target="_self"&gt;embodiment and situatedness&lt;/a&gt; (incidentally, the importance of which he had in fact &lt;em&gt;re&lt;/em&gt;discovered, as they had been discussed, among others, by members of the cybernetics movement way back in the 1950&amp;#8242;s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brooks tried to construct robots that could successfully operate in the noisy, complicated everyday world but he found he couldn't.
Most robots then, as now, are designed to operate in simplified environments so that the robot can respond to clear and unambiguous environmental
cues. These robots would expect objects to be placed in the same locations time after time, or read large clear black text on a white background.
These simple, structured environments were no match for the real world and the robots designed to operate in them couldn't operate when placed
in a house, or a street with a rough pavement and varying street lighting. This problem caused Brooks to draw a conclusion that proved to be
controversial within the field of artificial intelligence; that the mainstream symbolic approach was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the 1950's onwards (really ever since the
&lt;a title="Dartmouth Conference of 1956 at Wikipedia" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dartmouth_conference" target="_blank"&gt;Dartmouth Conference of 1956&lt;/a&gt;
), the mainstream approach to artificial intelligence was to represent the world as &lt;em&gt;propositions&lt;/em&gt; that could be manipulated. Propositions
are data items or symbols that  represent facts, objects in the environment, or abstract attributes. The propositions would be logically manipulated
using one of a variety of algorithms to solve a specific problem. Eventually, in order to apply any of the common methodologies and tools used by
artificial intelligence researchers such as Lisp, Prolog, or expert systems, the given problem had to be broken down as propositions, then
manipulated using a system of logical rules, then the answer would be presented as another list of propositions. This methodology is called
&lt;em&gt;functional decomposition&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the beginning of the eighties, the symbolic approach started to look shaky. Hubert Dreyfus criticized the approach on philosophical
grounds, whereas John Searle's Chinese Room argument and Joseph Weizenbaum's computer program Eliza highlighted grave drawbacks
in the symbolic approach. Their arguments were broadly pointedly ignored within the artificial intelligence field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the eighties, Brooks criticised functional decomposition as a means to design the control system of a robot. If you were to
functionally decompose a desired behaviour, you would divide the behaviour into individual functional tasks, such as pattern recognition,
language processing, and abstract reasoning. You would then treat each task as an individual problem to be solved. However, it is not at all
clear that tasks or behaviours are separated in this way in organisms. Evolution tends to produce highly integrated solutions that are not
easy to to decompose in the way a software engineering task may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead of using functional decomposition, Brooks urged the use of &lt;em&gt;behavioural decomposition&lt;/em&gt;. This approach breaks up behaviours
into a series of local actions. He suggested that modules that implement specific actions be triggered by specific cues. If a behaviour comes
from separate but cooperating actions responding to  local cues, it means that a robot doesn't need a central planning unit  to decide
what to do next. The overall behaviour of the robot emerges  from the local decisions made by various parts distributed about the  body of the
robot. This approach is bottom-up rather that top-down, the  very opposite of the functional decomposition method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brooks also suggested that every action should first be tested on the real robot placed in its operating environment to ensure that all the
actions work. Only once all the actions have been "debugged" should they be coordinated to compose more complex behaviours. The
robot should be repeatedly debugged until it performed the desired behaviours successfully. A real robot should be used rather than a simulation
since the real world (including the physical dynamics of the robot) is very hard to model, and really "the world acts as its own best
model". This means that instead of the robot responding to events that occur or are predicted to occur in a &lt;em&gt;model&lt;/em&gt; of the
environment, it would respond directly to an event in the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How has his ideas influenced evolved virtual creatures or evolutionary robotics? Well, an awful lot. Although he himself doesn't think
that evolved neural networks are the best technique to use, actually a robot controlled by a neural controller matches very closely his ideas
of individual actions triggered by specific cues. Such a robot is definitely behaviour-based. But most evolved robots are evolved in
simulation, not, as Brooks advocated, tested in the real world. The problem he has identified remains the biggest problem in evolved
morphology robots - how to transfer robots across the reality gap from simulation to the real physical world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Artificial Intelligence"></category></entry><entry><title>Virtual creatures gallery 2 of 10</title><link href="/virtual-creatures-gallery-2-of-10.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-08-10T10:24:00+01:00</published><updated>2010-08-10T10:24:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Ian Macinnes</name></author><id>tag:None,2010-08-10:/virtual-creatures-gallery-2-of-10.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is another post in an occasional series of other peoples&amp;' videos&lt;/a&gt; of evolved virtual creatures. I like these evolved
creatures by the &lt;a title="Evolution of Robotic Organisms home page" href="http://ero.matfyz.cz/" target="_blank"&gt;ERO&lt;/a&gt; group
(Evolution of Robotic Organisms). The swimming agents especially are wonderful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/0_8tNGKm87U" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The methodology is kept very close to that of Sims (e.g. same transfer functions …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is another post in an occasional series of other peoples&amp;' videos&lt;/a&gt; of evolved virtual creatures. I like these evolved
creatures by the &lt;a title="Evolution of Robotic Organisms home page" href="http://ero.matfyz.cz/" target="_blank"&gt;ERO&lt;/a&gt; group
(Evolution of Robotic Organisms). The swimming agents especially are wonderful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/0_8tNGKm87U" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The methodology is kept very close to that of Sims (e.g. same transfer functions such as abs, atan, cos, sigmoid, etc.) but
the most recent work applies the
&lt;a title="PDF of technical paper &amp;quot;Towards Efficient Evolutionary Design of Autonomous Robots&amp;quot;"
href="http://artax.karlin.mff.cuni.cz/~krcap1am/ero/doc/krcah49.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;NEAT crossover operator&lt;/a&gt; that allows
speciation within a population.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Artificial Intelligence"></category></entry><entry><title>The difference between being situated and being embodied</title><link href="/the-difference-between-being-situated-and-being-embodied.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-08-09T11:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2010-08-09T11:56:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Ian Macinnes</name></author><id>tag:None,2010-08-09:/the-difference-between-being-situated-and-being-embodied.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After discussing robots with a fellow artificial lifer, I can see confusion between two attributes of the physical existence of a robot or
organism. I want to clarify my definitions, at least to see if my use is compatible with others. These terms are &lt;em&gt;situatedness&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;embodiment&lt;/em&gt;. A physical agent …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After discussing robots with a fellow artificial lifer, I can see confusion between two attributes of the physical existence of a robot or
organism. I want to clarify my definitions, at least to see if my use is compatible with others. These terms are &lt;em&gt;situatedness&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;embodiment&lt;/em&gt;. A physical agent acting in the world is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;situated&lt;/strong&gt; such that the relationships between the  robot and the elements in its environment have a spatial and temporal
quality that varies as the robot moves; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;embodied&lt;/strong&gt; such that the body of a robot has its own physical dynamics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the problems tackled  by behaviour-based robotics use robots that react with objects that are spatially  located in the environment
(as opposed to symbolic objects or objects detected using magic sensors), and hence the robots are &lt;em&gt;situated&lt;/em&gt;. Including a
spatial element in the  relationship between the robot and   the object provides the robot with  feedback information that may be   complicated
to derive with a  non-situated controller. For example, a   phototactic robot is provided  with immediate feedback regarding its   orientation
from the varying  strength of the signals that are produced by its   sensors as the robot rotates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the controller of a real robot interacts with the environment through its body, and this body can have complex physical dynamics i.e.
it is also &lt;em&gt;embodied&lt;/em&gt;. If a robot is embodied, then it is very likely situated. Most simulated robots or animats are situated to some
degree, but they are not often embodied, especially with the very simple robots we use in artificial life experiments. This is because embodiment
refers to the physical existence of a robot or  organism, and it is more difficult to model the embodiment of a simulated robot than its
situatedness. If fact, sometimes the robot effectively has almost zero embodiment, but is only represented as little more than a position,
a radius, and an acceleration of movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is the distinction important?
&lt;a title="Rodney Brooks's home page" href="http://people.csail.mit.edu/brooks/" target="_blank"&gt;Rodney Brooks&lt;/a&gt;
believes that acknowledging embodiment is important because it encourages the robot's builder to
&lt;a title="PDF of Intelligence Without Representation by Rodney Brooks" href="http://people.csail.mit.edu/brooks/papers/representation.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;
continually test and correct&lt;/a&gt; the    robot's behaviour physically in the real world, a process that he compares with software debugging.
This debugging process must take place    on a real robot rather than a simulated or modelled robot because of    the difficulty of transferring
behaviours from simulation to reality.    Brooks also believes that debugging a real robot can reveal that some    problems which are difficult to
solve when considered in abstraction  do   not exist when a robot is physically constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For evolved robots that are to "cross the reality gap" to the real  world, it is essential we develop methodologies to model
a robot's  embodiment in such a way to make its behaviour transferable. The principle methodology we use is called minimal simulations,
which was first developed by Nick Jakobi in the mid nineties. This shall be the subject of a future post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Artificial Intelligence"></category></entry><entry><title>Virtual creatures gallery 1 of 10</title><link href="/virtual-creatures-gallery-1-of-10.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-08-08T13:09:00+01:00</published><updated>2010-08-08T13:09:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Ian Macinnes</name></author><id>tag:None,2010-08-08:/virtual-creatures-gallery-1-of-10.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm collecting videos of animats whose morphology and controllers have been evolved in order to improve my own video (and animat)
making ability. I'm looking for good visual designs and agents that &lt;em&gt;move&lt;/em&gt; naturally, even though they may not have a very lifelike
body shape. I'll start with the granddaddy …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm collecting videos of animats whose morphology and controllers have been evolved in order to improve my own video (and animat)
making ability. I'm looking for good visual designs and agents that &lt;em&gt;move&lt;/em&gt; naturally, even though they may not have a very lifelike
body shape. I'll start with the granddaddy of them all - virtual creatures created by
&lt;a title="Karls Sims' home page" href="http://www.karlsims.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Karl Sims&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/JBgG_VSP7f8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were the first virtual creatures developed, way back in 1994 and I suspect still the most visually striking. They use a simple
&lt;a title="PDF of technical paper &amp;quot;Evolving Virtual Creatures&amp;quot;" href="http://www.karlsims.com/papers/siggraph94.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;
developmental algorithm for the morphology and a unique controller&lt;/a&gt;, a hybrid of neural network and various functions to generate different
activation patterns that are used to control the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also evolved creatures to &lt;a title="PDF of technical paper &amp;quot;Evolving 3D Morphology and Behavior by Competition&amp;quot;"
href="http://www.karlsims.com/papers/alife94.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;compete against each other&lt;/a&gt;. The agents do not have much in the way of
sensors and so this was really a different evolutionary pressure for movement rather than coordinating perceptual and action.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Artificial Intelligence"></category></entry></feed>